Guide to the Diana Trilling Papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Diana Trilling Papers,
1921-1996
Trilling, Diana, 1905-1996
29.75 linear feet (57 document boxes, 2 oversized boxes)
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library, New York, NY. 10027
MS#1421
6259383
The Diana Trilling Papers document the life of literary and cultural critic, Diana Trilling. This collection contains her writings, extensive correspondence with other New York intellectuals, and subject files for her research as well as for the Lionel Trilling Estate.
Biographical Note
Writer Diana Trilling spent much of her life carving a niche out for herself that would separate her from her husband, critic and author, Lionel Trilling. Although she was fiercely devoted to their marriage, she maintained her own identity and had a successful career as a literary critic, an author, and a cultural commentator. She was not afraid to shy away from controversy especially if, in her view, her political opinions were being distorted or misunderstood by others. (The name Trilling, when used alone, refers to Diana Trilling. Lionel Trilling will always be referred to by his full name.)
Diana Rubin was born in New York City on July 21, 1905. Her parents, Joseph Rubin and Sadie Helene Rubin (neé Forbert), were immigrants from Poland. Joseph Rubin was a successful businessman while his wife did occasional work in interior design. Diana Rubin lived first in Westchester and then Brooklyn where she attended Erasmus Hall High School. She entered Radcliffe College in 1921 as an Art History major with a minor in Music. Rubin had wanted to be a singer, but had suffered from an affliction of the thyroid, effectively ending any chances she may have head to pursue a professional career.
After graduating cum laude in 1925, she moved back to New York to look for a job in some artistic environment, preferably a museum. What she found was a young graduate student at Columbia named Lionel Trilling. After dating for a couple of years, they married on October 25, 1929. Lionel Trilling continued to pursue his doctorate in English Literature while Diana Trilling spent her time volunteering in Harlem. She was active with other politically-minded individuals who were trying to save the Scottsboro Boys, the nine black boys charged with raping two white women in Scottsboro, Alabama. Diana Trilling tried to work with her Harlem neighbors and raise money to pay lawyer fees, a situation made more difficult due to racial and economic factors that distanced residents from each other.
In 1941, Lionel Trilling was asked by editors at The Nation to suggest a fiction critic for them. Diana Trilling offered her services and the weekly column "Fiction in Review" was created. The column ran until 1949. At this point, Trilling had begun contributing pieces on literary, social, and political themes for some of the following publications: The New York Times Book Review, Partisan Review, Commentary, Harpers, The Atlantic, The Saturday Review, Redbook, McCall's, Esquire, Mademoiselle, Vogue, The Nation, and The New Leader. Later on while being interviewed, she always made the point that she never discriminated against a particular journal or magazine. In other words, it was a privilege to know that one's articles were wanted in intellectual journals as well as mainstream magazines. In addition to these pieces, Trilling edited the Portable D.H. Lawrence for Viking Press in 1947. She was an active writer throughout her life and yet, found time to raise a family. James Lionel Trilling was born in 1949.
In the 1940s and 1950s, both Diana and Lionel Trilling began to distance themselves politically from other New York intellectuals. Once staunch supporters of Communism, they were unhappy with whom their fellow communists supported during World War II and the actions conducted in Europe under the umbrella of Communism. The Trillings joined the American Committee for Cultural Freedom. The American branch of this organization was in essence an Anti-Communist set of intellectuals and public personas that strove to condemn censorship of art and defend civil liberties. The group was comprised of individuals who represented various fields such as literature, dance, art, as well as political and labor activists. Notable members included Sidney Hook, James T. Farrell, Peter Viereck, W.H. Auden, George Balanchine, Saul Bellow, Elia Kazan, Robert Motherwell, Jackson Pollock, A. Philip Randolph, John Steinbeck and Robert Penn Warren. Diana Trilling served as Chairman of the Board from 1953 to 1957 and as a board member from 1957 until she resigned three years later. Trilling felt that she had moved away politically from some of the leadership and wanted to distance herself from their cause.
During this time, Lionel Trilling taught English at Columbia University. He was an extremely popular public figure who was always receiving invitations to give lectures, be a visiting scholar, or to read and offer criticism to literary pieces. Although he may have been more well-known of the two, Diana Trilling continued to publish articles and books. In 1958 she edited a selection of letters of D.H. Lawrence. This was followed by a collection of essays in 1964 published under the title Claremont Essays. The Trillings lived on Claremont Avenue and Diana Trilling felt that her address, and her neighborhood, had such an impact on the way she viewed the world.
Lionel Trilling was diagnosed with a rapid moving cancer in spring of 1975. His health quickly declined and he passed away in November of that same year. Despite this personal tragedy, Diana Trilling continued to write. Two years after his death, she published a retrospective of her time at Radcliffe College and the impression that coeducation made on the students of the mid-1970s called We Must March My Darlings. That same year Trilling began editing a twelve-volume uniform edition of her husband's works. This project lasted until 1979. In between, she pulled together some of her more popular book reviews and published Reviewing the Forties. Other publications include a nonfiction analysis of a 1981 Westchester murder trial entitled Mrs. Harris: The Death of the Scarsdale Diet Doctor, and a 1993 memoir of her marriage, The Beginning of the Journey: The Marriage of Diana and Lionel Trilling.
Throughout her career, Diana Trilling was active in intellectual and social organizations. Among them were the Radcliffe Club, the Cosmopolitan Club, which she joined in 1968, and the American Academy of Arts and Sciences, which she was elected to in 1976. She was also an honorary member of the Radcliffe Chapter of Phi Beta Kappa. Trilling also successfully received a joint grant from the Rockefeller Foundation and the National Endowment for the Humanities (NEH) and two Guggenheim Fellowships, one in 1950 and one in 1991.
Diana Trilling remained a public figure even when she was not at the peak of her career. Her fiery public outbursts, like the Lillian Hellmann controversy, and her outspoken nature, made her a controversial figure. Even when her eyesight was failing and she was diminishing her creative output, Trilling continued to praise the political and cultural time of the 1930s and criticize the social movements of the 1960s. Like her husband, she was often considered elitist and woefully ignorant of the ways in which the United States in general, and New York in particular, had moved on since the 1930s.
Despite the criticisms, Diana Trilling remained determined to defend her views and those of her husband. She continued to give interviews and mentor younger writers until her death from cancer in 1996. She is survived by her son James Trilling, an art historian
Photo Credit: Michael O'Neill
Scope and Content
This collection holds the papers of author, literary critic, and cultural commentator, Diana Trilling. Along with her husband, Lionel, Diana Trilling was a force on the New York intellectual scene from the 1930s until the 1970s. The records that comprise this collection document her professional life as well as her marriage with Lionel Trilling and the ways in which she balanced the two.
The bulk of the records are Diana Trilling's writings in the form of manuscripts, articles both published and unpublished, drafts and research notes. Correspondence with Lionel Trilling and other family members, publishing houses, and colleagues are also well represented. Other records include personal documents, photographs, subject files used for research and maintaining the Lionel Trilling Estate, and audio visual material.
Much of the records contained here provide insight or overlap with those within the Lionel Trilling Papers (MS#1256). These papers were donated soon after his death in 1976; however Diana Trilling continued to conduct his literary affairs on his behalf until her death in 1996.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in six series:
Series I: Personal Documents, 1921-1970
Series II: Correspondence, 1927-1996
Subseries II.1: Alphabetical, 1939-1996
Subseries II.2: Chronological, 1927-1996
Series III: Writings, 1929-1996
Subseries III.1: Manuscripts and Drafts, 1964-1995
Subseries III.2: Articles and Essays, 1929-1996
Series IV: Subject Files, 1924-1996
Subseries IV.1: Diana Trilling, 1924-1996
Subseries IV.2: Lionel Trilling, 1960-1996
Series V: Photographs, 1920s-1990s
Series VI: Audio Visual Material, 1956-1981
Related Material
Lionel Trilling Papers, 1899-1987,
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library
MS#1256
The American Committee for Cultural Freedom Records,
Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives,
Tamiment 023
Subjects
Barzun, Jacques, 1905-; Trilling, Diana.; Trilling, Lionel, 1905-1975.; Anti-communist movements--New York (State)--New York.; Criticism--United States.; Literary quarrels.; Women authors, American.; Women critics--United States.
Access Restrictions
This collection is located off-site. You will need to request this material at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.This collection has no restrictions
This collection has no restrictions.
Acquisition
Estate of Diana Trilling, Purchase, 1998
James Trilling, Purchase 2002
Theodore Solotaroff, Donation, 2006
- Series I: Personal Documents, 1921-1970
  This small series is composed of personal documents from Diana Trilling's early life. Academic records from her time at Radcliffe College, such as report cards, printed material and an autograph book, legal records concerning family members, yearbooks from Camp Lenore, course schedules from a vocal music institute, and a diary are found here. There is also a representative sample of appointment books and a family financial ledger.
  - General, undated, 1921-1930 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Address Book, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Appointment Books
    - undated, 1927-1931 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - 1960-1963 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - 1972-1977 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - 1980 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Barnard Certificate of Honor, 1989 April 5 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Biographical Statement (two drafts), [1982] (Box 60, Folder 1)
  - Diary, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - LenorLog, 1922-1924 (Camp Lenore) (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Lowell Institute, 1922 March-April (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Radcliffe College, 1923-1925, 1959, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Rubin, Cecelia, 1973 February 9 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Rubin, Joseph--Trust Fund, 1934-1940 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Rubin, Joseph--Will, 1934 June 13 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Trilling, Diana--Will, 1949-1951 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Trilling, James--Wedding, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Trilling, Lionel--Trust Fund, 1949 April 22 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Trilling, Lionel--Will, 1931-1951 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - War Rations, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Series II: Correspondence, 1927-1996
  Series II holds Diana Trilling's correspondence. Letters within this series are between other family members, members of the literary community like other authors and publishing houses, fans of her work, friends of both Diana and Lionel Trilling, and invitations to lecture, write or review a literary text. In most cases, the carbon copy of Diana Trilling's initial letter or response to a letter has survived as well as any accompanying documents. The original order of the series consisted of two subseries: one arranged alphabetically and one chronologically. This has been maintained.
  - Subseries II.1: Alphabetical, 1939-1996
    Letters found in Subseries 1 tend to be from Diana Trilling's friends and other family members and are often quite extensive. The Trillings had many friends in common so individuals such as Jacques Barzun, James and Elsa Grossman, Alan Ginsburg and Christopher Zinn have letters in this subseries. Correspondence with Nicolas Nabokov in regards to the American Committee for Cultural Freedom and Diana Trilling's subsequent resignation from the board are also held here. Of interest are letters between Diana Trilling and Lillian Hellman during the time that the two women were publicly fighting over politics and the "correct" history of the intellectual movement of New York within the 1930s and 1940s. Please note that although there are a few letters between Diana and Lionel Trilling, most are located in the Lionel Trilling Papers.
    - Anderson, Quentin and Thelma, 1958-1979 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - A through Barzun, 1939-1979 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Beichman, Arnold, 1952-1979 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Bell through C, 1939-1979 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - D through F, 1939-1979 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Grossman, James and Ella, 1963-1975 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - G through H, 1939-1979 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Hays, Elinor, 1964-1965 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - I through L, 1939-1979 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - M, 1939-1979 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - N through Q, 1939-1979 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - R, 1939-1979 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - S, 1939-1979 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - T through W, 1939-1979 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - A through B, 1980-1985 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - B, 1980-1985, (2 Folders) (Box 5, Folder 4 to 5)
    - C through D, 1980-1985 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - E through G, 1980-1985 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - H, 1980-1985 (includes Hellman letters) (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - I through L, 1980-1985 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - M, 1980-1985 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - M through R, 1980-1985 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - S, 1980-1985, (2 Folders) (Box 7, Folder 1 to 2)
    - Trilling, James, 1984-1985 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - T through Z, 1980-1985 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - A, 1986-1996 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - B, 1986-1996, (2 Folders) (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - B, 1986-1996 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - C through D, 1986-1996 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - E through G, 1986-1996 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - H through J, 1986-1996 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - K through L, 1986-1996 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - M, 1986-1996, (2 Folders) (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - M, 1986-1996 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - N through Q, 1986-1996 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - R, 1986-1996 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - S, 1986-1996, (2 Folders) (Box 9, Folder 4 to 5)
    - T through V, 1986-1996 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - W through Z, 1986-1996 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Subseries II.2: Chronological, 1927-1996
    Correspondence contained in Subseries 2 covers a variety of topics. Letters are from personal friends (and may be addressed to both Diana and Lionel Trilling), potential publishers and magazine editors who are inviting Diana Trilling to submit a piece or coordinating the publishing of one her books, other authors inquiring about the craft of writing, fans, individuals who criticize Trilling's many writings and, in particular, the type of political and culturally-biased perspective she employs, and distant relatives. There quite a number of condolence letters from Lionel Trilling's colleagues at Columbia University and other academic institutions, his many personal friends, and admirers, who knew him only through his body of work. This correspondence illuminates the kind of impact Lionel Trilling had, not only on the intellectual world, but on the world at large
    - 1927-1943 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - 1944-1945 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - 1946-1947 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - 1948-1949 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - 1950-1951 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - 1952-1955 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - 1956-1957 May (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - 1957 June-1958 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - 1959 January-May (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - 1959 June-1960 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - 1961-1962 April (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - 1962 May-1963 May (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - 1963 June-1964 April (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - 1964 May-December (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - 1965 January-June (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - 1965 July-1966 February (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - 1966 March-1967 February (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - 1967 March-December (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - 1968 January-July (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - 1968 August-December (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - 1969 (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - 1970 (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - 1971 (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - 1972 (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - 1973 (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - 1974 (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - 1975 January-October (Box 15, Folder 3)
    - 1975 November-December (Box 15, Folder 4)
    - 1975--Condolences
      - A through H (Box 15, Folder 5)
      - I through R (Box 16, Folder 1)
      - S through Y (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - 1976 January-March (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - 1976 April-August (Box 16, Folder 4)
    - 1976 September-December (Box 16, Folder 5)
    - 1977 January-April (Box 17, Folder 1)
    - 1977 May-September (Box 17, Folder 2)
    - 1977 October-1978 January (Box 17, Folder 3)
    - 1978 February-July (Box 17, Folder 4)
    - 1978 August-1979 January (Box 17, Folder 5)
    - 1979 February-September (Box 18, Folder 1)
    - 1979 October-December (Box 18, Folder 2)
    - 1995-1996 (Box 18, Folder 3 to 4)
    - Accession 2002, 1928-1991 (Box 18, Folder 5 to 6)
- Series III: Writings, 1929-1996
  Series III is one of the largest series is in the collection and is composed of Diana Trilling's diverse array of writings. Like her husband, Lionel Trilling, Diana Trilling was a prolific writer whose work was published in a variety of journals and magazines. She first submitted pieces for publication in the 1920s and was asked to contribute work up until her death. Within this series are manuscripts with multiple drafts, articles and essays, book reviews, and lectures. This series has been further arranged into two subseries.
  - Subseries III.1: Manuscripts and Drafts, 1964-1995
    The first subseries holds manuscripts and drafts for Diana Trilling's major books: Claremont Essays, The Beginning of the Journey and Mrs. Harris: The Death of the Scarsdale Diet Doctor. There are also chapters of her childhood memoirs and material concerning her marriage to Lionel Trilling that is separate from the texts used in The Beginning of the Journey. These drafts exist in multiple forms. Many of them went through several versions before the final one. In most cases, they are heavily annotated by Diana Trilling. In addition to the manuscripts themselves, there is often accompanying material for the individual titles consisting of correspondence with publishers, printed material for publicity purposes, and some reviews of the individual manuscripts.
    - The Beginning of the Journey
      - Correspondence, 1993-1995, (2 Folders) (Box 19, Folder 1 to 2)
      - Draft--General, 1993 (Box 19, Folder 3)
      - Draft--Chapter Three, 1993 (Box 19, Folder 4)
      - Final Draft I, 1993 (Box 19, Folder 5)
      - Final Draft II, 1993 (Box 19, Folder 6)
      - Final Draft III, 1993 (Box 20, Folder 1)
      - Notes, 1993, (2 Folders) (Box 20, Folder 2 to 3)
      - The Paris Review, 1993 (Box 20, Folder 4)
      - Review, 1993-1995 (Box 20, Folder 5)
    - Childhood Memoir
      - Chapter One, 1983 (Box 20, Folder 6)
      - Chapter Two, 1983 (Box 20, Folder 7)
      - Chapter Three, 1983 (Box 20, Folder 8)
      - Chapter Six, 1983 (Box 21, Folder 1)
      - Chapter--Excerpts, 1983 (Box 21, Folder 2)
      - Chapter--Father, 1983 (Box 21, Folder 3)
      - Chapter--High School, 1983 (Box 21, Folder 4)
      - Chapter--Kindergarten, 1983 (Box 21, Folder 5)
      - Chapter--Radcliffe College, 1983 (Box 21, Folder 6)
      - Chapter--War in Europe, 1983 (Box 21, Folder 7)
      - Final Draft I, 1983 (Box 21, Folder 8)
      - Final Draft II, 1983 (Box 22, Folder 1)
      - Final Draft III, 1983 (Box 22, Folder 2)
    - Claremont Essays
      - Draft, 1964, (2 Folders) (Box 22, Folder 3 to 4)
      - Reviews, 1964-1965 (Box 22, Folder 5)
    - Memoirs of a Marriage
      - Draft, 1990s (Box 22, Folder 6)
      - Final Draft, 1990s (Box 60, Folder 2)
      - Interview Transcript, 1990s (Box 60, Folder 3)
      - Notes, 1990s (Box 22, Folder 7)
    - Mrs. Harris: The Death of the Scarsdale Diet Doctor
      - General, undated, 1981 (Box 23, Folder 1)
      - Clippings, 1980-1981 (Box 23, Folder 2)
      - Contract, 1981 (Box 23, Folder 3)
      - Correspondence
        - Harcourt Brace Jovanovich, Inc., 1980-1981 (Box 23, Folder 4)
        - Legal Matters, 1981-1982 (Box 23, Folder 5)
        - Public, 1981-1984, (3 Folders) (Box 23, Folder 6 to 8)
      - Drafts
        - Discards, 1981, (2 Folders) (Box 23, Folder 9)
        - Discards, 1981 (Box 24, Folder 1 to 2)
        - Manuscript, 1981, (4 Folders) (Box 24, Folder 3 to 6)
        - New York Times Magazine, 1981 (Box 25, Folder 1)
      - Edited Galleys, 1981, (5 Folders) (Box 25, Folder 2 to 5)
      - Edited Galleys, 1981 (Box 26, Folder 1)
      - Hamish Hamilton Limited, 1981-1982 (Box 26, Folder 2)
      - Interviews, 1981 (Box 26, Folder 3)
      - Insurance, 1981 August 24 (Box 26, Folder 4)
      - Notes--Courtroom, 1980, (3 Folders) (Box 26, Folder 5 to 7)
      - Notes--Courtroom, 1980, (3 Folders) (Box 27, Folder 1 to 4)
      - Notes--Non-Courtroom, 1979-1980 (Box 27, Folder 5)
      - Notes--Non-Courtroom, 1979-1980, (2 Folders) (Box 28, Folder 1 to 2)
      - Penguin Books, 1981-1982 (Box 28, Folder 3)
      - Publicity--Post-Publication, 1981-1988 (Box 28, Folder 4)
      - Publicity--Pre-Publication, 1980-1981 (Box 28, Folder 5)
      - Reviews
        - America, 1981-1982 (Box 28, Folder 6)
        - Australia, 1982 June-July (Box 28, Folder 7)
        - England, 1982 May-July (Box 28, Folder 8)
      - Serialization, 1981-1982 (Box 28, Folder 9)
      - Shana Alexander, 1983 March (Box 29, Folder 1)
      - Stranger in Two Worlds, 1986 (Box 29, Folder 2)
      - Transcriptions, 1980-1981 (Box 29, Folder 3)
    - Reviewing the Forties 1978-1979 (Box 29, Folder 4)
    - We Must March My Darlings
      - "Daughters of the Middle Class," 1977 April 26 (lecture) (Box 29, Folder 5)
      - Draft I, 1976 (Box 29, Folder 6)
      - Draft II, 1976 (Box 29, Folder 7)
      - Draft III, 1976 (with research material) (Box 29, Folder 8)
      - Final Draft, 1977, (3 Folders) (Box 29, Folder 9 to 11)
      - Final Draft, 1977 (Box 30, Folder 1 to 2)
      - "A Return to the Past," 1971-1972 (chapter) (Box 30, Folder 3)
      - Reviews, 1977 (Box 30, Folder 4)
  - Subseries III.2: Articles and Essays, 1929-1996